Last week, we've built a computer that
can run a code, machine language code.
Two weeks ago, we've actually
programmed in machine language, but
we didn't really program in binary code,
but rather in assembly language
in some kind of nice syntax.
So, there is a gap in the middle, and
the gap is supposed to be a simple
software program called an Assembler.
So, specifically,
you've seen this slide already twice.
Two weeks ago, you've seen this slide
to focus on the left-hand side and
the actual assembly language format in
which you were supposed to program.
That was your eh,
perspective two weeks ago.
Your perspective last week was what
happened on the right-hand side,
the machine language, since you had
to actually construct a computer
that can actually execute the 1s and
0 that you see on the right.
Our focus, our perspective this
week is going to be on the middle,
how do you go from left to route,
how do you do, from left to right.
How do you do the operation
the assembly operation?
I.e., how do you, what is the assembler,
which is a program that translates what
you have on the left, the, the, the
assembly language code to what you have on
the right, the machine,
machine language code.
Now notice it's, for the first time
in this course, this is software.
This soft, this is going to be a program
that takes as input a file written
in the left hand side format,
i.e., in assembly language, and
produces another file that's written
in the right-hand side format i.e.,
as zeros and ones, which directly
can be executed on a computer.
So this is a software, the first time
that you do software in this course.
Until now, we, it was always hardware.
And it's really the first software
layer In every arg, in every eh,
the first software layer that
basically we have in every computer.
There are much more,
there is much more software above it, but
this is the first level,
and we're doing it together with the
hardware to give us a complete picture.
So we can have a computer that we
can understand how you program it.
And understanding how you program it does
not mean programming it in zero and ones,
but rather in assembly language
which is still is a very,
very low format essentially
equivalent to machine language.
But still it's something
that humans can relate to.
So let's see what kind of software
is this going to be, this assembler.
In principle,
you've only, we've only created a computer
that can run machine language code.
So, in principle, we should write our
program in the only language that can be
directly executed, i.e.,
in machine language code in zeros and
ones, which is going
to be pretty annoying.
But, the best way to think about it
is that we're not writing the first,
we're not constructing the first computer
in the world, but rather the second one.
So, let us assume we
already have a computer
that can run some high-level language.
In particular,
I'm talking about your computer and
the high-level languages
that you already know.
So, we are going to write
the assembler in that language, and
it will be a software program
that runs on your computer.
What it's going to produce, the machine
language it is going to produce,
is machine language for the HACK computer,
for a different computer,
the computer on which you will
actually run the produced program.
So we're thinking about cross-compilers,
some, sometimes it's called.
It's running on one computer and producing
code intended for another computer.
This way, we don't have this loop,
we don't have this bootstrap problem of
having to write our
assembler in machine code.
But rather we can write it already
in the high-level language that we
have already implemented
on another computer.
So the Assembler program is
really a very simple program.
It does the following basic loop and
repeats it again and again.
It reads one Assembly language
command from the input.
It basically breaks it into its parts,
and each one of its parts can be
translated to binary in a unique way
that's specified by our language.
And then we take the binary code of the
different parts, put them together, and
we get the machine code that directly
is equivalent to the Assembly language
command that we've just read.
We output that, and we move on to
the next Assembly language command.
We keep on doing that and
translate one command after another
without having to remember anything that
happened in the history, very simple.
So let's look at the different stages,
each one of these different stages,
slightly more carefully.
So how do we read the next
Assembly language command?
Well, it seems that we just read
the next line from the input.
This is almost exactly what we do.
The only, the only other
difficulty is that we may need to,
to skip what's called white space,
for example, comments.
We need to make sure that we read
what is really the next command and
not any kind of a comment, or any type of
spaces, or blank lines that are with it.
So when we read it from the file, we have
this file that, let's say, has a command
Load R1, 18, and this is just
a fictional language, Assembly language.
Later in the next unit we'll start
actually talking about the Hack len,
language specifically, but
in this unit I'm still focusing on
a generic Assembly Assembler program.
So let's assume that our
hypothetical Assembly language
has this type of command, Load R1,
18, which we expect is the,
would probably mean taking the value 18
and putting it into the first register.
But this is not something
that we need to go,
to know when we're actually
doing this translation.
We actually want to read that command and
put it into some kind of string variable,
into some kind of array of characters
that we can later work on.
And that is basically what's involved in
reading a line by line from the input.
So the next step is taking
this string of characters and
breaking it into its different parts.
So when we look at it,
we see that the different parts of
this command are Load, first part.
R1 should be the second part.
18 should be the third part.
Each one of them has meaning.
And there is also a space and a comma.
But these are not really
the interesting parts of the command,
but rather just some syntax, which helps
us break and understand what's written,
the important part in the command.
So, the next thing we have to do is
basically understand the syntax and
break the original string into these three
different, if you wish, sub-strings,
the three different interesting parts
that are involved in this command.
So that involves basically some
kind of simple string manipulation
until we get the different parts.
Once we have these different parts, then
we will need to translate each one of them
to machine language, to actually its
binary pa, its binary counterpart.
Now, how do we do that?
That has to be part of the specification
of the machine language and
assembly language.
Basically tells us what is the code for
each one of these commands, for example.
So it would, so for example, eh, the Load
command, we would probably have some kind
of table, which tells us, what is the
machine language code for each command?
In particular,
we can look up in that table and
see what is the machine language code for
the Load command.
Other parts of the input may be, for
example, numbers or maybe other things,
that we can directly translate into
machine language just because they
are numbers.
For example,
the number 18 may be translated
into just into the binary
representation of the number 18.
Again, this is part of
the language specification.
This is a basic part.
This is the part where we need to
understand exactly the mapping between
Assembly language and
machine language, which is ully,
usually very simple, and specified
completely by a bunch of tables and
a bunch of rules of where you put
integer numbers in the binary form.
And that's about it.
The third part is now we have basically
the translation of each part of the input
and we need to put them together,
usually just some kind of concatenation.
Maybe we will need to put also some
kind of other bits that are defined in
the specification to actually pad them and
complete the language.
Because sometimes the translation of
a mach, of a command does not fill all
the available bits that are,
are available in the machine.
And the other bits are specified to be
some, let's say, a constant 0 or 1.
So now we have basically the number,
the binary number that we need to output,
and we just need to print it out into the,
well, some kind of file.
How exactly we print it out is according
to, there's going to be some kind of
specification of the file
format of machine language,
which may be a binary format,
which may be just in characters 0 and 1.
That would be not something that
you would usually have, and so on.
But then you just need to basically
translate the numbers you have in your
memory, the 1s and
0s you have in your now, in your memory.
You have to translate that into a format
that the machine language can actually,
that the computer can actually execute.
So far, we've described the basic
operation of the assembler.
And now there's one extra complication
that we need to worry about, and
that is symbols, handling symbols.
As you may recall, one of the major
services that an assembly language
gives a programmer is the ability to
use symbols rather than direct numbers.
And we usually use them for
two different types of things.
One of them is for labels in the programs
to jump into a certain part the a program.
You give it a name rather than
really hard code the address.
And the other is you want to give
a variable name rather than el,
always refer to some to its
exact address in memory.
So for example, we can write and
view most assembly languages, JMP loop.
And loop of some kind,
is going to be translated automatically
into some kind of address.
Similarly, we can load into
a register a variable weight.
And again, weight is going to
be some location in memory
which the assembler needs to figure
out which location and will basically
translate this access directly to
accessing that location in memory.
So basically what our
assembler will have to do
is replace each one of these symbols.
For example, the weight in the,
in the previous eh, in the previous
command into its equivalent address, and
it will have to remember where
exactly that address in the memory.
Similarly, it will replace the, the, the
label of a loop of a jump with the exact
address inside the program and
again, remember where that is.
How does that happen
how will that be done?
Wel,l it will need to maintain some kind
of sym, of, of table that basically has
the, the information about the translation
between symbols and actual addresses.
And whenever it needs
to do this translation,
it will have to actually
look up in the table.
It sees weight in the assembly
language program.
It will have to look up in the table and
see what is the correct
address to put instead of it.
Once it's replaced
the symbol with a address,
then it can continue as
we previously described.
So let us see now how do
we maintain such a table,
how do we enter information into it, and
how do we look up information from it.
So for example, let's say we, now our
assembler is reading command by command,
and it encountered this command
with a variable weight in it.
So, maybe the variable is already in the
table, we need to look it up in the table.
If it's already in the table,
then we know exactly how to translate it.
This is the easy part.
But what happens the first time
we see this variable, weight?
Well, we look at it, we look in the table,
and we see that it's not there.
So, we know that we need to allocate
a new memory location to had,
to hold this variable.
And this is one of the things that
our assembler will have to do.
So, it will actually find the next
memory location that's available, and
the exact definition of where
does it allocate memory addresses
should be part of the assembly,
assembly language specification.
And it will basically allocate
this new memory to the symbol.
And now, it has this pair of symbol memory
address that it can put into the table,
and use from now on, including for now.
And this is how, basically,
we put a variable locations into
the table, and how we use them.
The other kind of la, the other kind
of symbol that we have are labels.
So let's see we have, well, let's see,
for example, we have a piece of
code that has inside, that had in it
a label loop, what does this mean?
When our assembler actually looks and
reads this line,
label, it knows well this is just a label,
it's not a real command to execute.
But I have to remember that the next
time somebody wants to jump
to this symbol loop,
I have to remember where exactly it is.
Where is it?
Well, I have to remember where,
what address is the current
command going to be put into the,
into, into the memory.
And that is going to be the address
that's referred to by loop.
So for example, if our,
prog, if our current,
if this current piece of program
is being allocated into,
being put,
being written into memory location 671,
672, 673, and so on,
of the program memory.
When we see this label,
our assembler will have to remember
the next program is program 673.
So I need to remember that loop from
now on always refers to location 673.
And this is basically the kind
of thing that it needs to do.
And then, when we actually get
to a place that uses this label,
uses this symbol, then we already know,
we already have in our table what
exactly is the correct address.
So that's basically how information is,
about labels, is put into the table and
read from it when needed.
Now, there's one extra complication
that we didn't talk about.
That sometimes we can use,
we can jump into a label before
the label was actually defined.
This is called a forward reference.
So for example, it's very common in,
in programs that I will need to jump,
let's say, into a label called continuing,
cont, before the label actually
occurred in the program.
If that is the case,
when I reach the first jump, when I first,
the, the jump instructions,
it uses a label.
That happens before I've already seen
the place that defines the label
in the label command, and how can I handle
that because it's not in the table yet.
Well, there are two ways to handle it.
One way, which is usually a little bit
more complicated, is to basically remember
that I've seen the labels, and
I don't know where it is yet.
Keep it in a side table.
And when I actually get into
the definition of the correct address,
fix it back.
Another, another option,
which turns out to be sometimes easier,
is that I actually do
everything in two passes.
In the first pass, I read everything
only paying attention to the labels and
remembering where each label refers to.
That, that's when i actually
build the table for the labels.
And only on the second pass do I
actually go and put and convert each and
every label into its correct code,
into its correct address,
that now is already in the table,
because I put it there in the first pass.
And that's a usual,
usually slightly easier to do, but
you may use each one of
these two possibilities.
So now we've finished talking about the
general process of creating an assembler,
the general thing that
an assembler must do.
And what we're going to do in
the next few units is start talking
specifically about the Hack
machine assembler and
talk about the different parts of
how you actually construct it.